Finding aid for the Exhibit Collection of Near Eastern Manuscripts, 1492-1848 LSC.1656
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Manuscripts
  - Divan-i ?afi? / Poems of ?afi?, 1831; Manuscript no. 8; 74 leaves: paper, ill.; 346 × 215 mm. bound to 349 × 220 mm. (Box 2)
    Belles-lettres. The anthology of the lyrics and poems of ?afi?.
    Author: ?afi?, 14th cent.
    Scribe: ?li Ashraf Khan
    Layout: Average of 25 lines of text per page; some pages have 4 columns.
    Decoration: Leaves 1b and 6a are illuminated.
    Binding: Lacquered painted boards with gold floral and bird ornamentation on a black background, framed in gold, red, and black borders. Inside covers depict a perched bird in gold on a red background, framed in gold and black borders.
    Additional description: Ornate title page illumination. Poems generally in black ink. Quatrains towards the end of the text are designated with red ink headings. Some staining.
    ff. 1b-3a: Prose introduction
    ff. 3b-6a: Opening verses
    ff. 6a-73b: Poems.
  - Qur'ān / Koran, n.d.; Manuscript no. 10; 7 leaves: paper, ill; 218 × 147 mm. (Box 2)
    Fragment containing parts or all of four short chapters 84 to 87, including: verses 16 to 25 of al-inshiqaq (The sundering), all of al-Burῡj (The mansions of the stars), all of al-Ṭāriq (The morning star), and verses 1 through 14 and the first two words of verse 15 from al-A̒alá (The most high).
    Language: Text in Arabic
    Layout: Average of 11 lines of text per page.
    Decoration: Illuminated.
    Additional description: One quire. Text in black ink, with every first, fifth, and eleventh line in larger script.
  - Tuḥfat al-zā ̒ir / The pilgrim's gift, 1830; Manuscript no. 11; 304 leaves: paper, ill.; 229 × 141 mm. bound to 231 × 144 mm. (Box 2)
    Scope and Content note
    Religion. Majlisῑ's Ṣafawid-period treatise on pilgrimage, with a guide for reading one's fortune using the manuscript written on the very last leaf (304b). The author states that he wrote the book in Persian because most people could not read the Arabic books written on this topic.
    Author: Majlisī, Muḥammad Bāqir ibn Muḥammad Taqī, 1627 or 8-ca. 1699
    Binding: Lacquered painted boards with decorative floral ornamentation.
    Additional description: Text in black ink with gilt ruling; chapter headings in red and framed in gold. Occasional spelling errors and marginalia. Water damage. Paper fragments laid in provide bibliographical information about two other manuscripts, one them is in the present collection (ms. 25).
    ff. 1b-2b: Opening
    ff. 2b-10a: Introduction
    ff. 10a-18b: Chapter one: the merits of repairing the holy tombs of the Prophet and the Imams, the merits of making pilgrimage to them, and the manner of making pilgrimage to them
    ff. 18b-36b: Chapter two: on the merit [?] and quality of making pilgrimage to the Apostle of God, Fa?ima Zahrá, and the Imams
    ff. 36b-77b: Chapter three: on the merit of making pilgrimage to [?li] and the quality of making pilgrimage to him
    ff. 77b-93a: Chapter four: on the merit of the noble Najaf, Kifa, the mosques of Kifa, and the waters of Euphrates
    ff. 93a-118b: Chapter five: on the merit of making pilgrimage to the Lord of the Martyrs, ?usayn ibn ?li
    ff. 118b-133a: Chapter six: on the merit of the glorious burial place and Karbala, and the merit of the tomb of Imam ?usayn, and the manner thereof
    ff. 133a-187b: Chapter seven: on the separated pilgrimages of his highness, which are not special to particular times, and the manners thereof, and other acts and prayers which must be done in the holy mausoleum
    ff. 187b-221a: Chapter eight: on the merit and quality of making pilgrimage to his highness which is special to known times and days
    ff. 221a-239b: Chapter nine: on the merit and quality of making pilgrimage to their highnesses Imam Misá Ka?im, Imam Ri?a, and Imam Mu?ammad Taqi
    ff. 239b-257b: Chapter ten: on the merit and quality of making pilgrimage to their highnesses Imam ?li Naqi, Imam ?asan ?skari, and the Lord of the Event
    ff. 257b-296a: Chapter eleven: on visiting the mosque where every Imam can be visited there
    ff. 296a-304a: Chapter twelve: on the manners of making the pilgrimage on another's behalf, and the manners of making the pilgrimage to the ofsprings of the Imams
    ff. 304a: Closing.
  - Al-daftar al-tas? min al-dafatir al-marsima bi al-Sulaymaniyya / The ninth book of the books styled al-Sulaymaniyya, 1593; Manuscript no. 12; 81 leaves: paper; 250 × 141 mm. bound to 250 × 145 mm. (Box 3)
    This manuscript is the ninth part of Kemalpasazade's Histories of the Ottoman House, entitled Tevârî?-I Âl-I O smân. The text describes the end of Bayezid II and the beginnings of Selim's reign.
    Author: Kemalpasazade, 1468 or 9-1534
    Scribe: Mu?ammad ibn A?mad al-Waqi? [al-Wafi"?]
    Language: Text in Ottoman Turkish
    Origin: Ottoman Empire
    Layout: Average of 17 lines of text per page.
    Binding: Quarter leather binding with decorative purple wrappers over stiff paper boards.
    Additional description: Text boxes, chapter headings, punctuation marks, and words introducing poetry in red ink. Leaf 59b entirely in red ink; leaves 72 and 79 are blue. Some spelling errors and marginalia.
    ff. 1b-2b: Brief opening
    ff. 2b-3b: Death of Bayezid, Selim mourns
    ff. 3b-6a: Selim ascends the throne, Ahmed rebels
    ff. 6a-8a: Selim deals with brothers and nephews
    ff. 8a-10a: Ahmed returns from Arab provinces, defeated outside Yenisehir
    ff. 10a-11a: Süleyman appointed Emir
    ff. 11a-18a: Kizilbas (Qizilbash) movement in Azerbayjan
    ff. 18a-18b: The army gathers, ready to set out
    ff. 18b-22a: Selim sets out, holds court in the field
    ff. 22a-24b: Correspondence with Shah Isma'il leads to war. Selim marches to Çaldiran
    ff. 24b-29a: Battle of Çaldiran, Selim victorious
    ff. 29a-30b: Victory-letters dispatched about
    ff. 30b-32b: Selim enters Tabriz
    ff. 32b-36b: Selim leaves Tabriz for Rim
    ff. 36b-39b: Invasion of the isle of Rhodes
    ff. 39b-42b: Marine "gaza" from Gallipoli
    ff. 42b-49b: Selim sets out on victorious journey and raises imperial standards
    ff. 49b-51a: Crossing into Rhodes, intending "gaza"
    ff. 51a-53b: Orders battle, councilors and commanders plot the taking of fortifications
    ff. 53b-57b: Ruler of Egypt joins the "gaza"
    ff. 57b-62a: Instruction on the capture of enemy, battle
    ff. 62a-65a: Ruler of Egypt dies
    ff. 65a-67b: Ottoman forces lay siege to the fortress
    ff. 67b-69a: What was taking place in surrounding kingdoms while the siege continued
    ff. 69a-72a: Assault on the fortress
    ff. 72a-77a: Residents of the fortress sue for peace
    ff. 77a-79b: Rhodes fortress taken
    ff. 79b-81a: Triumphant return home.
  - Humayin nama, ya, Mavahib-i ilahi / Book of Humayin, or, Divine gifts, n.d.; Manuscript no. 13; 271 leaves: paper; 243 × 122 mm. bound to 244 × 126 mm. (Box 3)
    Yazdi's history of the Mu?affarid dynasty of Shiraz, Isfahan, Kirman, and Yazd, written for Shah Shuja? in 1356 CE. The text appears incomplete, as it begins mid-sentence on the first page and ends abruptly on the last. It begins with the ancestry of his majesty the "Asylum of the Caliphate" (i.e Mubariz al-Din Mu?ammad), and mentions the birth of his sons Sharaf al-Din Shah Mu?affar, "Asylum of the Sultanate" (i.e Shah Shuja?), and Shah Ma?mid. It lays the ground for their further eminence, describing their meetings with the Ilkhanid Emperors Sultan Abi Sa" id and Arpa, and also mentions the affairs of the Injiids in Fars and the Chibanids.
    Author: Mu?in al-Din Yazdi, d. 1387
    Origin: [Persia?]
    Additional description: Chapter headings in red. Some stains and discoloration.
    ff. 3b-9a: Introduction
    ff. 9a-271a: The text.
  - Akhlaq al-Muhsini / The morals of the beneficent, 1802; Manuscript no. 14; 102 leaves: paper; 248 × 140 mm. bound to 255 × 146 mm. (Box 3)
    Islamic philosophy and ethics. Kashifi's moral treatise, dedicated to the Timurid Sultan ?usayn Bayqara circa 1494 CE.
    Scribe: ?bd Allah ibn ?bd Allah ibn ?bd Allah
    Language: Persian
    Layout: 16 lines of text per page.
    Binding: Brown leather binding with gilt stamping on spine.
    Additional description: Chapter headings and verse markers in red ink. Text and outer page margins have been colored.
    ff. 1a-4a: Opening
    ff. 4a-4b: Table of contents
    ff. 4b-5a: Chapter one: worship
    ff. 5a-5b: Chapter two: purifying
    ff. 5b-6a: Chapter three: prayer
    ff. 6a-7a: Chapter four: thanksgiving
    ff. 7a-8a: Chapter five: patience
    ff. 8a-8a: Chapter six: contentment
    ff. 8a-8b: Chapter seven: reliance on God, and the ability to live without
    ff. 8b-10b: Chapter eight: having shame
    ff. 10b-10b: Chapter nine: chastity
    ff. 10b-11b: Chapter ten: courtesy
    ff. 11b-12b: Chapter eleven: eminence of resoluteness
    ff. 12b-13a: Chapter twelve: purposefulness
    ff. 13a-14a: Chapter thirteen: endeavoring and struggling
    ff. 14a-15a: Chapter fourteen: steadfastness
    ff. 15a-23a: Chapter fifteen: justice
    ff. 23a-25a: Chapter sixteen: forgiving
    ff. 25a-26b: Chapter seventeen: restraint
    ff. 26b-27b: Chapter eighteen: affability and benignity
    ff. 27b-29b: Chapter nineteen: mercy and clemency
    ff. 29b-31b: Chapter twenty: good works and charity
    ff. 31b-34b: Chapter twenty one: generosity and beneficence
    ff. 34b-37a: Chapter twenty two: humility and respectfulness
    ff. 37a-38b: Chapter twenty three: trustworthiness and religiosity
    ff. 38b-41a: Chapter twenty four: loyalty to a pledge
    ff. 41a-41b: Chapter twenty five: honesty
    ff. 41b-42b: Chapter twenty six: bringing about the needs of others
    ff. 42b-43b: Chapter twenty seven: deliberation and careful regard
    ff. 43b-45b: Chapter twenty eight: consultation and planning
    ff. 45b-46b: Chapter twenty nine: vigilance and foresight
    ff. 46b-51a: Chapter thirty: bravery
    ff. 51a-53b: Chapter thirty one: zeal for honor
    ff. 53b-55b: Chapter thirty two: management
    ff. 55b-59b: Chapter thirty three: being wakeful and informed
    ff. 62a-63a: Chapter thirty five: concealing secrets
    ff. 63a-65b: Chapter thirty six: taking advantage of opportunity
    ff. 65b-72a: Chapter thirty seven: honoring the rights
    ff. 72a-74b: Chapter thirty eight: conversing with those who are upright
    ff. 74b-82b: Chapter thirty nine: repulsing rascals
    ff. 82b-102a: Chapter forty: on training servants and retainers, and their manners.
  - Tu?fat al-a?rar va … sub?at al-abrar / The gift of the free and ... the majesty of the upright, [1450-1550?]; Manuscript no. 15; 168 leaves: paper, ill.; 197 × 105 mm. bound to 210 × 108 mm. (Box 3)
    Belles-lettres. The manuscript contains two works. From ff. 1b-63a is Tu?fat al-a?rar, and from 64b-168a is Sub?a al-abrar. Both works are part of the "septet" of Jami, or Haft Awrang.
    Origin: [Timuird Herat?]
    Layout: Average of 15 lines of text per page; two columns.
    Decoration: Pages 1b-3a, and 64b-66b are illuminated.
    Binding: Black leather binding with red leather inside covers.
    Additional description: Text in black ink; lacks chapter headings.
    ff. 1a-1b: Opening
    ff. 1b-63a: Tu?fat al-a?rar
    ff. 64b-168a: Sub?a al-abra.
  - Târih-i feth-i Belgrad; Târih-i Bosna / The history of the conquest of Belgrade; History of Bosnia, 1741 March; Manuscript no. 16; 167 leaves: paper, ill.; 204 × 154 mm. bound to 204 × 155 mm. (Box 3)
    The manuscript contains two historical works. The History of the conquest of Belgrade is an excerpt from Subhî's Tarih-I Sami ve Sakir ve Subhî (Istanbul, 1784) covering the reign of the Ottoman Sultan Mahmud (r. 1730-1754). The scribe begins with the events of the year 1736 C.E. (80a of the printed work) when the troubles with Afsharid Persia are brought to a close, and the Ottoman army heads west into the Balkans. To this excerpt, the compiler has added a selection by Ömer Bosnavi entitled Târih-I Bosna (History of Bosnia), known by its full title as Tarih-i Bosna der zaman-i Hekimzade Ali Pasa.
    Author: Mehmet Subhî, d. 1769 and Ömer Bosnavi, 18th cent.
    Layout: Average of 23 lines of text per page.
    Binding: Deteriorated brown leather binding with blind stamped leather cutout on cover; leather fore-edge flap.
    Additional description: Text in black ink, punctuation marks (often misplaced) in red. Chapter headings and verse markers in red from ff. 72b-117b.
    ff. 1b-117b: Târih-i Feth-i Belgrad
    ff. 119b-167a: Târih-i Bosna.
  - Ḥālnāmah / The book of ecstasy, 1566?; Manuscript no. 17; 17 leaves: paper, ill.; 218 × 143 mm. bound to 222 × 146 mm. (Box 3)
    Belles-lettres. Mystical story in verse, also known as Guy va chawgan, ya, Ḥālnāmah (The ball and polo stick, or, The book of ecstasy).
    Author: ?arifi, d. ca. 1449
    Layout: Average of 12 lines of text per page.
    Script: Nasta̒ lῑq.
    Decoration: Illumination on title page; paper is painted in blue and gold floral motifs.
    Binding: Red leather binding with three medallions blind stamped on cover.
    Additional description: The leaves decorated in yellows, greens, and blues, with gold floral motifs. The text in black, chapter headings in gold.
    Content:
    ff. 1b-5b: Opening
    ff. 5b-11a: Narrative
    ff. 11a-17a: Closing.
  - / [Letter-writing], n.d.; Manuscript no. 18; 67 leaves: paper; 180 × 127 mm. bound to 181 × 126 mm. (Box 3)
    This is a handbook of official correspondence, meant for secretaries, providing samples of letters to various government functionaries or potentates according to rank or the occasion. These include letters congratulating a person's appointment to the office of grand vizier (5a), a vizier's letter to the king (8b), or letters congratulating scholars being appointed to teach and to give legal rulings (16b).
    Layout: Average of 15 lines of text per page.
    Binding: Brown leather binding with gilt medallion stamped on covers; detached fore-edge flap. Decorative green, red, and white endpapers.
    Additional description: Official correspondence manual. Text in black and red ink.
    ff. 1b-5a: Opening
    ff. 5a-65b: Sample letters
    ff. 65b-67b: Blank.
  - Qur'ān / Koran, n.d.; Manuscript no. 19; 1 leaf, 1 fragment: paper; 123 × 80 mm., 21 × 78 mm. (Box 2)
    Fragment of Chapter 8 (Sira al-Anfal, or the Spoils of war) from the fourth word of verse 15 to the very end of verse 72. Small fragment from Chapter 3 (Sira al ?Imran, or The family of Amram): recto has five words (the fourth, fifth, sixth, seventh, and eighth) from the 195th verse; verso has seven words of the 198th verse.
    Layout: 15 lines of text.
    Decoration: Chapter headings in gold.
    Additional description: Text in black ink, vowels in red ink. Framed in gold border.
  - Qur'ān / Koran, [18--?]; Manuscript no. 19; 605 leaves: paper, ill.; 257 × 162 mm. bound to 259 × 166 mm. (Box 5)
    Koran with interlinear Persian translation, as well as exegetical marginalia attributed to "Husayn Kashifi", who may be the same 15th-16th century intellectual Husayn Va'iz Kashifi (d. 1504-5) of the Timurid court in Herat.
    Language: Text in Arabic and Persian
    Origin: [Qajar Persia?]
    Script: Naskh (Arabic text), nast? liq (Persian text).
    Decoration: Extensive, full-leaf illumination on leaves 1b, 2a, 2b, 105b, 106a, 201b, 202a, 292a, 293b, 374b, 375a, 448b, 449a, 518b, 519a, 604b, and 605a. Partial illumination throughout entire manuscript.
    Binding: Red lacquer boards; red leather spine. Dense floral design on the outside covers, medallions on inside covers.
    Additional description: Arabic text in black, interlinear Persian in red, and marginalia in black and red. The text is framed in a box with thin green, gold, red, white, and blue borders. Between this box and the edge of the paper, there is another gold border 13 × 16 mm. from the edge of the paper. Extensive marginalia in red and black ink.
  - / [Calendar], [1775]; Manuscript no. 20; 8 leaves: paper; 244 × 155 mm. bound to 253 × 163 mm. (Box 3)
    A calendar of the year 1189-90 AH (1775-6 AD), completed under the reign of the Ottoman Sultan Abdulhamid I (r. 1774-89), who is mentioned in the opening statements (1b). Each page covers a month in the Islamic calendar. For each month there is a table listing the weeks, "Arabic" and "Roman" dates of the week, the houses of the zodiac, and suitable activities. The author mentions a day in April 1775 as the first day of Spring (Nowrooz/Nevruz) and the day when the year will change; therefore the composition must have been completed shortly before that time. Gilt stamp on cover reads "Universal calendar of 1190 for Sultan Abdulhamid I."
    Language: Ottoman Turkish
    Layout: Average of 12-15 lines of text per page.
    Binding: Half leather binding with decorative blue paper; red, green and gray botanical print endpapers.
    Additional description: Text in black, orange, green, gold, and red ink. Ink-stained, chipped and frayed.
- Scrolls
  - [Scroll], [18--?]; Manuscript no. 21; 1 roll (20 sheets): paper, ill.; ca. 680 cm. × 10 cm. (Box 7)
    8 rolls, mostly illustrated, glued together into a consecutive piece.
    Decoration: Decorated with the following illustrations in order of appearance from top of the scroll to the bottom
    A) brown cross with green wreath on top, planted into green earth
    B) Jesus dressed in red and blue, surrounded by three winged faces
    C) section historiated with three figures in same positions--an angel, a bear or lion, and a donkey or goat, each with a red fish-tale and holding a book
    D) black cross
    E) red and gold cross
    F) Jesus dressed in red and blue with his hand on the head of a man dressed in green, kneeling before him
    G) gold cross on red and black platform set on pink paper
    H) red cross with two angels hovering at the foot, set on yellow paper.
    Occasional stains and tear drops. Handwritten note dated 1952, possibly regarding the scroll, wrapped with the item.
    Language: Text in Armenian
  - [Scroll], [18--?]; Manuscript no. 22; 1 roll (4 sheets): paper, ill.; 117.8 cm. × 10.5 cm. (Box 7)
    Layout: Four small scrolls glued together.
    Decoration: Painting at head of scroll of Jesus with a gold halo, dressed in red and blue. Watermark at head of scroll.
  - [Scroll], 1835; Manuscript no. 23; 1 roll: paper; 106 cm. × 8.7 cm. (Box 7)
    Contains Koranic and exegetical matters. Introduction torn away, with remaining text beginning with the middle of the 255th verse ("Aya al-Kursiyy" or the "Verse of the throne") of the second sira ("al-Baqara" or the "Cow"); ending at verse 257. This is followed by a phrase in red, "what is to follow after prayer," and then text in black ink, ending with an "invocation to Ali" prayer. Includes beginning of sira 97 or "al-Qadr" ("Power"). The tail of the scroll contains closing statements, verses in Persian, and a date mark. Layout: Ruled lines of text enclosed in a gold and blue text box. Paper is frayed and torn at head.
  - [Scroll], 1842; Manuscript no. 24; 1 roll: paper; 58.6 cm. × 12 cm. (Box 7)
    Layout: Ruled text in black ink, framed in painted orange borders. Torn at the top and bottom; frayed around the edges.
  - [Scroll], 1842; Manuscript no. 25; 1 roll: paper, ill.; 84.6 cm. × 7.8 cm. (Box 7)
    Unruled text in brown ink, heading in red ink, framed in red borders. Green cross at head of scroll.
  - [Scrolls], [18--?]; Manuscript no. 26; 8 rolls: paper, ill.; various sizes (Box 6)
    Layout: 8 separate scrolls, some illustrated.
  - [Scroll and purse], [18--?]; Manuscript no. 27; 1 roll, 1 pouch: paper, ill., cloth: scroll of unknown length, 173 × 183 mm. (Box 5)
    Layout: Black and red ink text in a red border. Cloth pouch of brightly colored fabric; small metal clasp. Scroll has fine and elaborate illustrations throughout. Scroll is fragile and light-sensitive. May not be handled without the express permission and supervision of the Manuscripts Librarian.
  - [Scroll], 1848; Manuscript no. 28; 1 roll (2 sheets): paper, ill.; 86 cm. × 10.5 cm. (Box 7)
    Layout: Scroll comprised of two pieces glued together. Decoration: Illustration of green and red cross at head of scroll. Text in black ink, with yellow borders. Watermark at head of scroll.
  - [Scroll], [18--?]; Manuscript no. 29; 1 roll (4 sheets): paper, ill.; ca. 10 × 125 cm. (Box 7)
    One scroll, divided into two fragments, comprised of two pieces glued together each.
    Decoration: Illustration of Jesus, dressed in red and blue. Text in black, framed in yellow borders.
  - [Scroll], 1839; Manuscript no. 30; 1 roll (2 sheets): paper, ill.; 118.4 cm. × 9.6 cm. (Box 7)
    Layout: Unruled text with section headings; ruled borders. Illustration of Jesus at head of scroll, dressed in blue and red with yellow halo. Text in black ink, with red or blue headings. Yellow and black borders. Undated notation, possibly regarding the scroll, wrapped around it.
  - [Scroll], [18--?]; Manuscript no. 31; 1 roll (2 sheets): paper, ill.; 133 cm. × 10.4 cm. (Box 6)
    Scroll begins with God's name at the top, followed by fifteen circular and one square text box, containing Arabic text and number charts. The texts are prayers and spells with repetitive phrases, some of which are from the Koran (for example, the text of the ninth circle begins with a few word of the Sira al-Qalam "Chapter of the Pen").
    Layout: Average of 10 lines of text within each circular frame; circles are approx. 8 cm. in diameter. Two pieces glued together to comprise one scroll.
    Decoration: Painted circle borders enclose the text; green and pink floral motif painted in the margins. Red, black, green and blue ink. The scrolls appear to have been folded lengthwise before rolling; a tear has occurred along the top 16.5 cm. of the seam.
  - [Scroll], 1833; Manuscript no. 32; 1 roll (2 sheets): paper; 84.4 cm. × 10.2 cm. (Box 7)
    Layout: Unruled text on two fragments. Text in black, red, orange, green, and blue ink, framed in brown and yellow borders. At the head of the scroll, a piece has been torn from the margin to the inner edge of the border, measuring 14.7 × 1.9 cm.
- Book covers and artifacts
  - [Leather bag], n.d.; Manuscript no. 33; 1 bag (accessory item): leather; 285 × 260 × 50 mm. (Box 4)
    Leather bag with braided tassels for securing the flap; leather braided shoulder-strap. The flap is embroidered with green and brown leather in geometric designs.
  - [Book cover], n.d.; Manuscript no. 34; 1 lacquered book cover: paper-mâché; 220 × 133 mm. (Box 4)
    Lacquered book cover with decorative floral ornamentation. Outside covers show a bouquet of various colors against a black background, framed in red and yellow floral borders; inside covers show red flowering plant framed in black and yellow floral borders. In black ink, "Part Eight; ?aji Mu?ammad ?aqi; ?aji Baba Tabrizi " on outside cover. Fly leaves attached.
  - [Book cover], n.d.; Manuscript no. 35; 1 lacquered book cover: paper-mâché; 193 × 120 mm. (Box 4)
    Lacquered book cover (one board) with ornamental design. Recto shows three floral medallions over a yellow background with red borders; red framed in black border on verso. English writing in pencil on verso: "used as a cover for tax sheets [illegible] bound with a string."
  - [Book cover], n.d.; Manuscript no. 36; 1 lacquered book cover: paper-mâché; 154 × 89 mm. (Box 4)
    Lacquered book cover with decorative floral ornamentation. Outside cover shows a floral design on red background, framed in gold and black borders; inside cover shows white flowering plant on orange background with blue and white borders.
  - [Book cover], n.d.; Manuscript no. 37; 1 leather book cover: paper-mâché: 172 × 94 mm. (Box 4)
    Red leather book cover (one board only) with painted cut-outs and gilt border.